As an archaeologist,
كعالمة آثار،
I'm most often asked what my favorite discovery is.
غالباً ما يتم سؤالي عن اكتشافي المفضل.
The answer's easy:
الإجابة بسيطة:
my husband, Greg.
زوجي، غريغ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We met in Egypt on my first dig.
التقينا في مصر في أول رحلة لي للتنقيب عن الآثار.
It was my first lesson in finding unexpected, wonderful things.
لقد كان ذلك أول دروسي في اكتشاف أشياء غير متوقعة ورائعة.
This began an incredible archaeological partnership.
وهذا بدوره بدأ شراكة أثرية مدهشة.
Years later, I proposed to him in front of our favorite pair statue
وبعد عدة سنوات، عرضت عليه الزواج أمام التمثالين المفضلين لنا
of the Prince and Princess Rahotep and Nofret,
للأمير رع حتب والأميرة نفرت،
in the Cairo Museum,
في متحف القاهرة،
dating to 4,600 years ago.
والذي يعود تاريخه إلى 4600 سنة.
I thought if I was going to ask Greg to spend the rest of this life with me,
لقد فكرت بأني إذا ما كنت أنوي سؤال غريغ قضاء بقية هذه الحياة معي
then I should ask him in front of two people
فحينها يجب أن أسأله أمام شخصين
who had pledged to be together for eternity.
تعاهدا على البقاء سوياً إلى الأبد.
These symbols endure because when we look at them,
فهذه الرموز تدوم لأننا كلما نظرنا إليها،
we're looking at mirrors.
نبدوا كأننا ننظر في المرآة.
They are powerful reminders
فهي تعتبر رسائل تذكير قوية
that our common humanity has not changed.
بأن إنسانيتنا المشتركة لم تتغير.
The thrill of archaeological discovery is as powerful as love,
إن إثارة الاكتشاف الأثري تعادل قوة الحب،
because ancient history is the most seductive mistress imaginable.
وذلك لأن التاريخ القديم هو أكثر السيدات اللاتي يمكن تخيلهن فتنة.
Many archaeologists have devoted their lives
الكثير من علماء الأثار كرسوا حياتهم
to unraveling the mysteries of the past
لحل ألغاز الماضي
under hot suns
تحت الشموس الحارة
and Arctic winds
ورياح القطب الشمالي
and in dense rainforests.
والغابات الاستوائية الكثيفة.
Many seek.
الأغلبية تطمح.
Some discover.
البعض يكتشف.
All worship at the temple of possibility
جميعهم يتبتلون أمام معبد الإمكانية
that one discovery might change history.
بأن اكتشاف واحد لربما يُغير التاريخ.
On my first day in Egypt, I worked at a site
في أول أيامي في مصر، عملت في موقع
in the Northeast Egyptian Delta called Mendes, dating to 4,200 years ago,
في شمال شرق الدلتا بمصر يدعى منديس، ويرجع تاريخه إلى 4200 سنة في الماضي،
in a cemetery.
في مقبرة.
That's a picture of me --
هذه صورة لي
I'm just in my bliss.
وأنا في منتهى السعادة.
On the dig, surrounded by emerald green rice paddies,
في رحلة تنقيب، محاطة بحقول أرز خضراء زمردية،
I discovered an intact pot.
اكتشفت إناء سليم.
Flipping it over,
عندما قمت بقلبه،
I discovered a human thumbprint left by whoever made the vessel.
وجدت بصمة إبهام إنسان تعود للشخص نفسه الذي صنع هذا الوعاء.
For a moment, time stood still.
للحظة، شعرت بأن الوقت توقف.
I didn't know where I was.
لم أكن أعلم أين أنا.
It was because at that moment I realized,
وذلك لأنه في تلك اللحظة أدركت حينها،
when we dig,
أنه عندما نقوم بالتنقيب،
we're digging for people,
فنحن ننقب عن أشخاص،
not things.
وليس أشياء.
Never are we so present as when we are in the midst of the great past.
نحن لا نكون حاضرين إلا عندما نكون في حضرة الماضي.
I can't tell you how many times I've stood in front of the Pyramids of Giza,
لا أستطيع إخباركم كم من المرات التي وقفت فيها أمام أهرامات الجيزة،
and they leave me speechless.
مذهولة، عاجزة عن الكلام.
I feel like the luckiest person in the world.
أشعر حينها بأني أكثر الأشخاص حظاً في هذا العالم.
They're a monument to our human brilliance and everything that is possible.
إنها معلمٌ تذكاري لمدى ذكاء الإنسان ولكل شيء ممكن.
Many cannot process their brilliance as human --
الكثير لا يستطيع تصور أن هذا الذكاء من صنع الإنسان،
they think aliens built them.
يعتقدون أن الفضائيون بنوها.
But this is ridiculous.
ولكن هذا مجرد سخف.
All you need to do is get up close and personal,
كل ما يجب عليك فعله هو الذهاب إلى هناك بنفسك،
and see the hidden hand of man
لترى يد الإنسان الخفية
in the chisel marks left by the tools that built them.
في علامات النحت التي خلفتها الأدوات التي قامت ببنائها.
The Great Pyramid of Giza was built one stone at a time
الهرم الأكبر في الجيزة تم بناؤه بحجر واحد في كل مرة
with 2.3 million blocks,
ويتكون من 2.3 مليون كتلة حجرية،
with incredible bureaucratic efficiency.
بكفاءة بيروقراطية لا تصدق.
It is not the pyramids that stand the test of time;
ليست الأهرامات ما يقف أمام اختبار الزمن،
it is human ingenuity.
بل هي براعة الإنسان.
That is our shared human brilliance.
هذا هو التألق الإنساني الذي نتشاركه جميعاً.
History may be cyclical,
ربما يكرر التاريخ نفسه،
but we are singular.
ولكن نحن استثنائيون.
I love what I do,
أنا أحب ما أفعله،
because I learn that we haven't changed.
لأنى أتعلم أننا لم نتغير.
I get to read about mother-in-law jokes from Mesopotamia
فقد قرات نكاتاً عن الحماة تعود لبلاد ما وراء النهر
from 3,500 years ago.
منذ 3500 عام مضت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I get to hear about neighbors cursing each other
وأسمع عن جيران يسبون بعضهم بعضاً
from 4,600 years ago in Egypt.
منذ 4,600 عام في مصر.
And my absolute favorite, from 3,300 years ago in Luxor:
والمفضل لدي على الإطلاق منذ 3,300 عاماً فى الأقصر:
an inscription that describes schoolboys who cut class to go drinking.
تسجيل يصف تلاميذاً يقطعون دروسهم للذهاب لشرب الخمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Kids these days.
أطفال هذا الجيل.
I get to see the most incredible architecture,
وقد رأيت أروع أساليب البناء،
see stunning sculptures --
رؤية منحوتات مذهلة
I mean, this is basically a selfie in stone --
أقصد أنه أشبه بصورة سيلفي في هيئة حجرية،
and see that we've always rocked serious bling.
ورؤية أننا دائمًا ما صنعنا مجوهرات مذهلة.
And also, we've been posting on walls
وأيضاً، كنا نقوم بالنشر على الحوائط،
and obsessing about cats --
ولدينا هوس تجاه القطط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
for thousands of years.
لآلاف السنين.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Archaeologists are the cultural memory preservers
علماء الآثار هم من يحفظ الذكرى
and the spokespeople
وهم أيضاً المتحدثون بالنيابة عن
for the billions of people and the thousands of cultures
ملايين البشر وآلاف الثقافات
that came before us.
التي أتت قبلنا.
Good science, imagination and a leap of faith
العلم الجيد، الخيال، والتحلى بالإيمان
are the trifecta we use to raise the dead.
هي التلاثي الذي نستخدمه لإحياء الموتى.
In the last year,
في السنة الأخيرة،
archaeologists have made incredible discoveries, including:
قام علماء الآثار باكتشافات مدهشة، تتضمن:
new human ancestors from South Africa;
أسلاف البشر في جنوب أفريقيا،
tools from 3.3 million years ago --
أدوات منذ 3.3 ملايين سنة
these are the oldest tools ever discovered --
وهي أقدم الأدوات التي تم اكتشافها،
in Kenya.
في كينيا.
And this, from a series of medical implements found
وهذه، ضمن سلسلة أدوات طبية عثر عليها
from Blackbeard's ship from 1718.
في سفينة بلاكبيرد منذ 1718.
What you're looking at is a medical tool used to treat syphilis.
وما تنظرون إليه الآن هو أداة طبية استخدمت لعلاج مرض الزهري.
Ouch!
مؤلم!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
For each of these,
ولكل واحدة من هذه،
there are thousands of other incredibly important discoveries
هناك آلاف من الاكتشافت المهمة والمدهشة
made by my colleagues,
والتي قام بها زملائي،
that do not make headlines.
ولكن لا تصل للعناوين الرئيسية.
However, I believe that the most important thing we do as archaeologists
ولكن، أنا مؤمنة أن أهم شيء نفعله كعلماء آثار
is acknowledge that past people existed
هو الاعتراف بوجود القدماء
and lived lives worth learning about.
وأن حياتهم تستحق الدراسة.
Can you even imagine what the world would be like today
هل تستطيعون تخيل كيف سيكون العالم اليوم
if we acknowledged all human beings in this way?
لو تعاملنا مع كل البشر بنفس الطريقة؟
So, on a dig, we have a challenge:
لذلك، نحن نواحهه تحديًا أثناء الحفر:
it often looks like this.
في كثير من الأحيان تبدو هكذا.
You can't see anything.
لا يمكن رؤية أي شيء.
Where are we going to start digging?
أين سنبدأ بالحفر؟
This is from a site south of Cairo.
هذا من موقع في جنوب القاهرة.
Let's have a look from space.
لنأخذ نظرة من الفضاء.
Again, you can't really see much.
مجددًا، لا تستطيع رؤية الكثير.
What you're looking at is a WorldView-3 satellite image,
ما تنظرون إليه هو صورة بالقمر الصناعي "WorldView-3"
which has a .3 meter resolution.
والذي يملك دقة تصوير تعادل 0.3 من المتر.
That's 10 inches.
ذلك يساوي 10 إنشات.
This means that you can zoom in from 400 miles in space
وهذا يعني أنه يمكنك تكبير من 400 كيلومتر في الفضاء
and see your tablets.
ورؤية جهازك اللوحي.
How do I know about this?
كيف علمت هذا؟
It's because I'm a space archaeologist.
ذلك لأني عالمة آثار فضاء.
Let me repeat that.
دعوني أعيدها ثانية.
I am a space archaeologist.
أنا عالمة آثار فضاء.
This means --
هذا يعني...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا.
This means I use satellite images and process them using algorithms,
هذا يعني أني أستخدم صور القمر الصناعي وأعالجها بالخوارزميات،
and look at subtle differences in the light spectrum
ثم أنظر إلى الاختلافات الدقيقة في الطيف الضوئي
that indicate buried things under the ground
والتي تشير إلى أشياء مدفونة تحت الأرض
that I get to go excavate and survey.
والتي يمكنني الذهاب والتنقيب عنها.
By the way --
بالمناسبة،
NASA has a Space Archaeology program,
ناسا تمتلك برنامج لعلم آثار الفضاء،
so it's a real job.
ولذا فهي وظيفة حقيقية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, let's have a look again.
دعونا نلقي نظرة مجددًا
We're back at the site just south of Cairo.
لقد عدنا للموقع بجنوب القاهرة.
You can't see anything.
لا تستطيع رؤية أي شيء.
Keep your eye on the red rectangle.
أبقوا عيونكم علي المستطيل الأحمر.
When we process the image using algorithms --
عندما نعالج الصورة بالخوارزميات،
think like a space-based CAT scan --
أشبه بالتصوير المقطعي للفضاء،
this is what you see.
هذا ما نراه.
This rectilinear form is an ancient tomb
هذا الشكل المسقيم الخطوط هو مقبرة قديمة
that is previously unknown and unexcavated,
لم تكن معروفة أو منقبة،
and you all are the first people to see it in thousands of years.
و أنتم أول من يراها من آلاف السنين.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I believe we have barely scratched the surface
انا أومن أننا بالكاد قمنا بخدش السطح
in terms of what's left to discover.
نسبة إلى ما بقي لنكتشفه.
In the Egyptian Delta alone,
في دلتا مصر فقط،
we've excavated less than one-1000th of one percent
لقد قمنا بحفر أقل من واحد من الألف من الواحد بالمئة
of the total volume of Egyptian sites.
من الحجم الكلي للمواقع في مصر.
When you add to that the thousands of other sites
عندما تضيف إلى ذلك آلاف المواقع الأخرى
my team and I have discovered,
التي اكشفها فريقي وأنا،
what we thought we knew pales in comparison
الذي اعتقدنا أننا نعرفه أصبح لا شيء بالمقارنة
to what we have left to discover.
مع ما تبقى لنكتشفه.
When you look at the incredible work
عندما تنظر إلى العمل الرائع
that my colleagues are doing all around the world
الذي يقوم به زملائي حول العالم
and what they're finding,
وما يقومون باكتشافه.
I believe that there are millions of undiscovered archaeological sites
أنا أومن أن هناك الملايين من المواقع الأثرية
left to find.
تبقت لإيجادها.
Discovering them will do nothing less
اكتشافها لن يفعل شيئًا أقل
than unlock the full potential of our existence.
من إطلاق العنان للإمكانات الكاملة لوجودنا.
But we have a challenge.
ولكن عندنا تحدي.
Over the last year,
على مدار العام الماضي،
we've seen horrible headlines
شاهدنا عناوين مروعة
of incredible destruction going on to archaeological sites,
من التدمير الكبير للمواقع الأثرية،
and massive looting by people like ISIL.
والنهب الهائل من جماعات مثل داعش.
ISIL has destroyed temples at Palmyra.
داعش قد دمرت معابد في بالميرا.
Who blows up a temple?
من يفجر معبد؟
They've destroyed the Tomb of Jonah.
لقد دمروا مرقد النبي يونس (عليه السلام).
And we've seen looting at sites so rampant,
ورأينا النهب يتفشى في المواقع،
it looks like craters of the moon.
مما جعلها تبدو كسطح القمر.
Knowing ISIL's desire to destroy modern human lives,
وبمعرفة أن داعش لديها توق لتدمير حياة الإنسان المعاصر،
it's a natural extension for them to destroy cultural identity as well.
ولذا فهم امتداد طبيعي لتدمير الهوية الثقافية أيضًا.
Countless invading armies have done the same throughout history.
عبر التاريخ هناك عدد لا يحصى من الجيوش الغازية التي فعلت المثل.
We know that ISIL is profiting from the looting of sites,
نحن نعلم أن داعش تربح من خلال تدمير المواقع،
but we don't know the scale.
ولكننا لا نعرف المقياس.
This means that any object purchased on the market today
وهذا يعني أن أي شيء يتم شراؤه من السوق الآن
from the Middle East
من الشرق الأوسط
could potentially be funding terrorism.
قد يكون تمويلًا للإرهاب.
When a site is looted,
عندما يتم نهب موقع،
it's as if a puzzle already missing 90 percent of it pieces
فالأمر يصبح أشبه بأحجية فقدت 90 بالمئة من قطعها
has had the rest obscured beyond recognition.
مما يجعل الباقي لا يمكن التعرف عليه.
This is ancient identity theft writ large.
إنها سرقة لهوية عتيقة مكتوبة بالخط العريض.
We know that there are two kinds of looting going on:
نحن نعلم أن هناك نوعين من النهب:
looting by criminal elements like ISIL,
النهب من جانب العناصر الإجرامية مثل داعش،
and then more local looting by those that are desperate for money.
ونهب محلي من أولئك اليائسين للحصول على المال.
We would all do the same to feed our families;
نحن سنفعل المثل لكي نطعم عائلاتنا،
I don't blame the local looters.
أنا لا ألوم النهاب المحليين.
I blame the middlemen, the unethical traffickers
أنا ألوم الوسطاء، المهربين
and an international art market
وسوق الفن الدولي
that exploits often ambiguous or even completely nonexistent laws.
الذين يستغلون قوانين غامضة أو حتى غير موجودة.
We know looting is going on on a global scale and it's increasing,
نحن نعلم أن النهب يحدث على صعيد واسع وفي ازدياد،
but presently we don't have any tools to stop it.
ولكن الآن ليس لدينا الأدوات التي توقفه.
This is beginning to change.
وهذا الأمر بدأ يتغير.
My team and I have just completed a study looking at looting in Egypt.
فريقي وأنا قد أكملنا للتو دراسة تبحث في عمليات النهب في مصر.
We looked at open-source data
لقد بحثنا في بيانات مفتوحة المصدر
and mapped the entirety of looting across Egypt
وعيّنا مواقع النهب في مصر
from 2002 to 2013.
من 2002 إلى 2013.
We found evidence of looting and site destruction at 267 sites,
وجدنا آثار نهب وتدمير ل267 موقع،
and mapped over 200,000 looting pits.
وعيّنا ما يزيد على 200,000 حفرة سرقة.
It's astonishing.
هذا مدهش.
And putting that data together --
وعند تجميع البيانات
you can see the looting pits marked here.
يمكنكم رؤية حفر النهب موضحة هنا.
At one site, the looting got bad from 2009, 2011, 2012 --
وفي أحد المواقع، أصبح النهب أسوأ من 2009، 2011، 2012
hundreds and hundreds of pits.
مئات ومئات الحفر.
Putting all the data together,
بتجميع كل البيانات،
what we found is that, contrary to popular opinion,
ما وجدناه يناقض الرأي العام،
looting did not start to get worse in Egypt in 2011 after the Arab Spring,
لم يصبح النهب أسوأ في مصر عام 2011 بعد الربيع العربي،
but in 2009, after the global recession.
و لكن في 2009، بعد الركود العالمي.
Thus, we've shown with big data
وبالتالي، فقد بيّنا باستخدام البيانات
that looting is fundamentally an economic issue.
أن النهب في الأساس هو مسألة اقتصادية.
If we do nothing to stop the problem,
إن لم نفعل شيئًا لوقف هذه المشكلة،
all of Egypt's sites will be affected by looting by 2040.
فكل المواقع المصرية سوف تتأثر بالنهب بحلول 2040.
Thus, we are at a tipping point.
وهكذا نحن عند نقطة فاصلة.
We are the generation with all the tools and all the technologies
نحن الجيل الذي يملك كل الأدوات والتكنولوجيا
to stop looting,
لإيقاف النهب،
but we're not working fast enough.
ولكننا لا نعمل بالسرعة الكافية.
Sometimes an archaeological site can surprise you with its resilience.
في بعض الأحيان يفاجئك موقع أثري بمرونته.
I am just back from the field,
أنا عائدة للتو من الموقع،
where I co-led a joint mission with Egypt's Ministry of Antiquities
حيث شاركت في قيادة بعثة مع وزارة السياحة المصرية
at a site called Lisht.
في موقع اسمه ليشت.
This site dates to the Middle Kingdom of Egypt between 2,000 and 1,750 BC.
هذا الموقع يعود إلى مملكة مصر الوسطى بين 2,000 و 1,750 قبل الميلاد.
The Middle Kingdom was Ancient Egypt's Renaissance period.
هذه المملكة تمثل فترة عصر النهضة في مصر القديمة.
After a time of intense internal strife and environmental challenges,
وبعد فترة الصراع الداخلي الشديد والتحديات البيئية،
Egypt rebounded
ازدهرت مصر
with an incredible resurgence of art, architecture and literature.
مع انتشار لا يصدق للفن والعمارة والأدب.
It's a favorite period of time to study in Egypt,
إنها فترة مميزة للدراسة في مصر،
because it teaches us so much about how we can survive and thrive
لأنها تعلمنا الكثير عن كيفية النجاة والتطور
after great disasters.
بعد الكوارث الضخمة.
Now at this site, we had already mapped countless looting pits.
الآن في هذا الموقع، قمنا بتعيين عدد لا يحصى من حفر النهب.
Lisht is a royal site;
ليشت يعتبر موقع ملكى،
there would have been thousands of people buried there
لا بد أن الآلاف قد دفنوا هناك
who lived and worked at the court of Pharaoh.
ممن عاشوا وعملوا في حكم فرعون.
You can see this before and after; you see dozens of looting pits.
بمكنكم رؤية هذا قبل وبعد يمكنكم مشاهدة العشرات من حفر النهب.
North Lisht.
شمال الليشت.
This is in South Lisht, before and after.
هذا جنوب الليشت، قبل وبعد.
When we first visited the site,
عندما زرنا الموقع لأول مرة،
we could see the tombs of many high-ranking officials
استطعنا رؤية مقابر أشخاص ذوي أهمية
that had been looted.
تعرضت للنهب.
Let me put into perspective for you what was taken.
اسمحوا لي أن أوضح ما قد تم اخذه.
Imagine a two meter by two meter area full of coffins, jewelry
تخيلوا منطقة بمساحة 2 متر مربع مليئة بالتوابيت، المجوهرات
and incredible statuary.
ومنحوتات جميلة.
Multiply that times over a thousand.
وضاعفوا هذا ألف مرة.
That's what was taken.
هذا ما قد تم أخذه.
So, when we started work,
عندما بدأنا العمل،
my Egyptian co-director, Mohamed Youssef, approached me and said,
قام مديري المصري، محمد يوسف، بالاقتراب مني وقال،
"We must work at this one particular tomb.
"يجب علينا أن نعمل على هذه المقبرة خصيصًا.
It's been attacked by looters.
لقد تعرضت للنهب.
If we don't do anything, they'll be back."
إن لم نفعل شيئًا، سوف يعودون."
Of course I agreed, but I didn't think we'd find anything.
وافقت بالطبع، ولكن اعتفدت أننا لن نجد أي شىء.
I thought the looters had stolen everything.
اعتقدت أن النهاب قد سرقوا كل شيء.
What we started to find were the most incredible reliefs.
ما بدأنا العثور عليه كانت نقوش لا تصدق.
Look at this painting -- it's just stunning.
انظروا إلى هذه اللوحة، إنها رائعة.
We started finding engraved inscriptions.
بدأنا بإيجاد نقوش محفورة.
And even the titles of the tomb owner --
وحتى ألقاب صاحب القبر
he had titles like, "Overseer of the Army,"
كانت ألقاب مثل "مشرف الجيش،"
"Overseer of the Treasury."
"مشرف الخزينة"
I began to have hope.
أصبح لدي أمل.
Maybe, just maybe we would find his name.
ربما، فقط ربما نجد اسمه.
For the ancient Egyptians, having their name last for eternity
عند القدماء المصريين، أن يكون اسمهم خالدًا
was their goal.
كان هو الهدف المنشود.
And then one day,
وفي يوم ما،
this appeared.
ظهر هذا.
This is the name of the tomb owner: Intef.
كان اسم صاحب المقبرة، إنتف.
You can see it written out here, in hieroglyphs.
يمكنكم رؤيته مكتوبًا هنا، بالهيروغليفية.
Working together with my Egyptian team,
بالعمل مع فريقي المصري،
we had restored someone's name from 3,900 years ago.
لقد استعدنا اسم شخص من 3,900 سنة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Working together with my Egyptian colleagues,
بالعمل مع زملائي المصريين،
we celebrated this moment of shared discovery.
احتفلنا بهذه اللحظة باكتشافنا المشترك.
What we were doing together was right and true.
ما كنا نفعله معًا كان صحيحًا وحقيقيًا.
We found this incredible false door, mostly intact.
وجدنا هذا الباب الوهمي، معظمه سليم.
On it we read about Intef and his inscriptions.
لقد قرأنا عن إنتف ونقوشه على هذا الباب.
You can actually even see him seated here.
يمكنك في الواقع أن تراه جالسًا هنا.
What I realized is that everything I had assumed about looted sites
ما أدركته أن كل شيء افترضته عن المواقع المنهوبة
had been proven wrong.
قد ثبت أنه خطأ.
Every day on site we worked together with 70 Egyptians
في كل يوم كنا نعمل مع 70 مصريّ
as colleagues and friends.
كزملاء وأصدقاء.
In the face of so much hatred and ignorance
في مواجهة الكراهية والتجاهل
against those in the Middle East,
تجاه الشرق الأوسط،
every moment on site felt like a protest for peace.
كل لحظة كانت أشبه بوقفة احتجاجية لنشر السلام.
When you work with those that don't look like you,
عندما تعمل مع أناس لا يشبهونك في الشكل،
or think like you, or speak like you,
أو يفكرون أو يتكلمون مثلك،
your shared mission of archaeological discovery
مهمتكم المشتركة في الكشف عن الآثار
erases all superficial differences.
تمحي كل الفروقات السطحية.
What I learned this season
ما تعلمته هذا الموسم
is that archaeology isn't about what you find.
أن علم الآثار ليس عبارة عن ما تجده.
It's about what you can prove possible.
ولكنه عبارة عن ما تستطيع إثبات إمكانيته.
Sometimes when you travel, you end up finding long-lost family --
أحيانا عندما تسافر، ينتهي بك الأمر بإيجاد عائلة فقدت منذ زمن،
not those with whom you share genes,
لا أقصد أولئك الذين تشاركهم الجينات،
but a shared entry in the book of life.
ولكن تشاركهم الدخول في كتاب الحياة.
This is Omer Farrouk, my brother.
هذا عمر فاروق، أخي.
Omer's a Gufti from a village just North of Luxor, called Guft.
عمر من قرية تدعى جوفت، قرية إلى الجنوب من الأقصر.
Guftis are part of a celebrated tradition in Egyptology.
الجوفتيون جزء من الثقافة المصرية.
They help with digging and work crew organization.
يساعدون في الحفر وتنظيم العمل.
Omer is my COO and CFO.
عمر هو رئيسي التنفيذي والمالي.
I simply couldn't do work without him.
ببساطة أنا لا أستطيع العمل بدونه.
One day many years ago, when I was a young graduate student
يومًا ما قبل عدة سنوات، عندما كنت طالبة صغيرة على وشك التخرج
and Omer was a young Gufti who couldn't speak much English,
وعمر كان جوفتي صغير لا يستطيع التحدث بالإنجليزية جيدًا،
we learned, completely randomly,
علمنا، بطريقة عشوائية تامة،
that we were born in the same year,
أننا قد ولدنا في نفس السنة،
the same month
نفس الشهر،
and the same day, six hours apart.
ونفس اليوم، مع فارق 6 ساعات.
Twins.
توأم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Separated by an ocean, but forever connected
منفصلين بمحيط، ولكن متصلين للأبد
for Ancient Egypt is our mother.
بمصر القديمة التي تعد أمّنا.
I knew then we'd always work together --
علمت حينها أننا سنعمل سويًا دائمًا،
not in my brain,
ليس في عقلي،
but in the part of your soul that knows not everything can be explained.
ولكن في ذلك الجزء من روحك الذي يعلم أنه ليس كل شيء يمكن تفسيره.
(Arabic) Omer by brother,
(بالعربية) عمر، يا حبيبي
I will always love you.
أنا بحبك جدا، على طول يا أخي.
(English) Omer my brother,
أخي عمر، سأظل أحبك.
So, just before my first dig in Egypt,
لذا مباشرة قبل الحفر الأول في مصر،
my mentor, the very famous Egyptologist Professor William Kelly Simpson,
معلمي، عالم المصريات الشهير جدًا البروفسور وليام كيلي سمبسون،
called me into his office.
دعاني إلى مكتبه.
He handed me a check for $2,000,
وأعطاني شيكًا ب 2,000 دولار.
and said, "This is to cover your expenses.
وقال "هذا لتغطية النفقات الخاصة بك.
Have a glorious adventure this summer.
فلتحظي بمغامرة رائعة هذا الصيف.
Someday you will do this for someone else."
ويوما ما سوف تفعلين هذا لشخص آخر."
Thus, my TED Prize wish is partial payback, plus interest --
وهكذا، أمنيتى لجائزة TED هي أن أرد ديني، زائد الفوائد،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
for a great human being's generosity and kindness.
لكرم هذا الإنسان ولطفه.
So, my wish.
لذا، أمنيتي.
I wish for us to discover the millions of unknown archaeological sites
أتمنى أن نكتشف كلنا ملايين الأماكن الأثرية غير المعروفة
around the world.
حول العالم.
By creating a 21st-century army of global explorers,
عبر إنشاء جيش من مستكشفي القرن الواحد والعشرين،
we'll find and protect the world's hidden heritage,
سوف نجد ونحمي تراث العالم الخفي،
which contains clues to humankind's collective resilience
الذى يحتوى على أدلة على براعة الإنسان
and creativity.
وإبداعه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا.
So how are we going to do this?
كيف سنفعل هذا؟
We are going to build with the TED Prize money
سوف نبني باستخدام المال من جائزة TED
an online, crowdsource, citizen science platform
منصة تعليمية على الإنترنت للمدنيين
to allow anyone in the world to engage with discovering
لتتيح لأي شخص في العالم المشاركة في اكتشاف
archaeological sites.
المواقع الأثرية.
There are only a couple hundred of us space archaeologists around the world.
هناك فقط بضع المئات منا علماء آثار الفضاء حول العالم.
It is my dream to engage the world
إنه حلمي جذب العالم
with helping to find sites and protect them.
للمساعدة في كتشاف المواقع وحمايتها.
What you'll do is sign in, create a username --
كل ما عليكم فعله هو تسجيل الدخول، إنشاء اسم مسخدم،
note that this particular username is already taken.
والتأكد أن هذا الاسم ليس مستخدمًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You'll take a tutorial and you'll start work.
سوف تأخذ جولة تعليمية ومن ثم ستبدأ العمل.
I want to note at the outset
أود أن أذكر في البداية
that in no way will be sharing GPS data or mapping data for sites.
أننا لن نقوم بأي حال من الأحوال بمشاركة المعلومات حول المواقع الجغرافية.
We want to treat them like human patient data,
نريد أن نعاملها مثل معاملة بيانات المرضى،
and not reveal their locations.
ولن نكشف عن مواقعها.
You'll then be dealt a card from a deck -- 20 x 20 meters or 30 x 30 meters,
وبعدها سيتم تسليمكم مسطح بمساحة 20x30 متر مربعأو 30x30 متر مربع،
and you'll be looking for features.
وستبحثون عن المعالم.
My team and I will have batch-processed
فريقي وأنا سوف يكون عندنا دفعة مجهزة
large amounts of satellite data using algorithms
من بيانات الأقمار الصناعية باستخدام الخوارزميات
in order for you to find things,
لكي تستطيعوا إيجاد أشياء،
so you'll be doing really good science.
ولذا سوف تنتجون علمًا جيّدًا.
You'll then be starting to look.
ومن ثم ستبدأون النظر.
What do you see? Do you see a temple?
ماذا ترون؟ أهو معبد؟
Do you see a tomb? Do you see a pyramid?
أهي مقبرة؟ أهو هرم؟
Do you see any potential site damage or site looting?
هل هناك أي احتمالية لتدمير أو سرقة موقع؟
You'll then begin to mark what's there.
ومن ثم ستبدأون بتمييز ما هناك.
And off to the side are always going to be rich examples
وعلى الجوانب سيكون هناك دائمًا أمثلة كثيرة
of exactly what you're seeing, to help guide you.
عما تراه تحديدًا، للمساعدة في الإرشاد.
All the data that you help us collect will be shared with vetted authorities,
جميع البيانات التي تساعدنا في جمعها، سوف يتم الاطلاع عليها من قبل السلطات
and will help create a new global alarm system
وسوف تساعدنا لخلق نظام إنذار عالمي جديد
to help protect sites.
لحماية المواقع.
But it's not just going to stop there.
لكن هذا لن يقف هنا فقط.
All the archaeologists with whom we share your discoveries
كل علماء الآثار الذين تشاركهم اكتشافك
will take you with them as they begin to excavate them,
سوف يأخذونك معهم وهم ذاهبون للحفر،
by using Periscope, Google Plus and social media.
باستحدام تطبيق بيرسكوب، جوجل بلس، ومواقع التواصل الاجتماعي.
A hundred years ago, archaeology was for the rich.
قبل مئة عام، كان علم الآثار للأغنياء.
Fifty years ago,
من 50 عامًا،
it was for men.
كان للرجال.
Now it's primarily for academics.
الان هو للأكاديمين.
Our goal is to democratize the process of archaeological discovery,
هدفنا هو إضفاء الطابع الديمقراطي لعملية الاكتشاف الأثري،
and allow anyone to participate.
والسماح لأي شخص بالمشاركة.
Ninety-four years ago,
من 94 عامًا،
Howard Carter discovered the tomb of King Tut.
اكتشف هوارد كارتر مقبرة الملك توت.
Who is the next Howard Carter?
من هو هوارد كارتر التالي؟
It might be you.
من الممكن أن يكون أنت.
By creating this platform,
عن طريق إنشاء هذه المنصة،
we will find the millions of places occupied by the billions of people
سوف نجد ملايين الأماكن المليئة بمليارات الناس
that came before us.
الذين جاؤوا قبلنا.
If we want to answer the big questions about who we are
إذا أردنا أن نجيب على الأسئلة الكبرى حول من نكون نحن
and where we've come from,
ومن أين أتينا،
the answers to those questions do not lie in pyramids or palaces,
الإجابة على هذه الأسئلة لا تكمن في الأهرامات أو القصور،
but in the cities and villages of those that came before us.
ولكن في المدن والقرى التي وجدت قبلنا.
If we want to learn about the past,
إذا أردنا أن نتعلم عن الماضي،
it's time we inverted the pyramids.
فقد حان الوقت لقلب الأهرامات.
Acknowledging that the past is worth saving
بالاعتراف أن الماضي يستحق الحفظ
means so much more.
يعني الكثير.
It means that we're worth saving, too.
هذا معناه أننا نستحق الحفظ أيضًا.
And the greatest story ever told
وأعظم قصة رويت
is the story of our shared human journey.
هي قصة رحلتنا البشرية المشتركة.
But the only way we're going to be able to write it
ولكن الطريقة الوحيدة لكتابتها
is if we do it together.
هي أن نفعلها سويا.
Come with me.
تعالوا معي.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)